Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project, 593058
  - Smith, Mozelle, 1974 May 2; 344195 (Box 56, Reel 187a - 187c)
    Mozelle Smith was born Marcella Gale at 504 West 125th Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She had one brother. Her mother migrated to New York from Chesterfield County, Virginia when she was 16 years old and worked as a chambermaid in apartments near Columbia University in Manhattan. Smith attended Public Schools 43 and 157 in the Bronx until the eighth grade. She earned her high school equivalency credential when she was 30 years old by attending night school at the Wadleigh School in Harlem. Smith married when she was 30 years old and raised her husband's two sons, but she did not have any children of her own. She worked in domestic service.
    This interview was conducted by Gigi, whose last name is unknown, on May 2, 1974. The location is likely Mozelle Smith's apartment. Gigi often provides long anecdotes of her own. This interview covers Smith's childhood in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York; her education; her work in domestic service; part of her mother's life in Chesterfield County, Virginia; a discussion between herself and Gigi about religion; and Smith's musings on how New York City and its inhabitants have changed since her childhood.
    Smith begins the interview by recounting how she received her nickname, Mozelle, in school and how the name has stayed with her. She describes growing up in Harlem and specifically focuses on living in racially mixed areas, both on 125th Street and 127th Street. She explains the impact this had on her education experience, noting that the first school she attended, Public School (PS) 43, was a predominantly white school, where the teachers treated her well, but she often fought with other students when they called her racial slurs. She recalls that when she transferred to PS 157, she expected to be treated fairly because there were more black students, but they ostracized her because she lived in a white neighborhood, which prompted fights with them. Smith recounts her mother not understanding her aggressive reaction to racial slurs and attributes this to her being accustomed to such treatment due to growing up in Virginia. She recounts her mother's time in Virginia and her experience migrating to New York; her mother's job as a chambermaid near Columbia University in Manhattan; the difference in the ways in which lighter and darker skinned black people were treated; and her experience at church and Sunday school.
    Smith and Gigi have a long discussion concerning religion, covering topics such as the difference in the way the black community and others practice religion; whether such a delineation should exist; changes in the importance of religion for both groups; and the impact of slavery and African traditions on the development of black spirituality. Other topics include Smith's musings on changes in New York City since her childhood; Spanish becoming as important a language as English in the United States at the time of the interview; her reasons for never having children; and comparing the connotations of being referred to as black or negro.
  - Sotello, Lebuncio, Undated; 344642 (Box 100, Cassette 332, Box 75, Reel 332a, Box 44, Reel 332b/150a)
  - Stackhouse, Ollie, 1975 November 11 and December 1; 344196 (Box 57, Reel 188a - 188e, Box 58, Reel 188f - 188i)
    Ollie Stackhouse was born in Rippon, West Virginia in 1912. She had four sisters and one brother. Her father worked on a farm and her mother worked as a midwife and domestic worker. Stackhouse migrated to Baltimore, Maryland in 1933 and later to New Jersey in the 1940s before finally settling in New York, New York in 1945. Stackhouse married in 1944 and had one son born in 1952. She worked in domestic service for various families in Rippon, Baltimore, and New York; as a cook at the Rainbow Room at 30 Rockefeller Center in the Midtown neighborhood of Manhattan; and as a worker in factories that manufactured slips and zippers in New York. She was a member of an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union).
    This interview was conducted by Karen Kearns on November 11 and December 1, 1975. The location is likely Ollie Stackhouse's home. The volume fluctuates and sometimes cuts out before resuming after a few seconds. This interview covers Stackhouse's childhood in Rippon, West Virginia; her migrations to Maryland, New Jersey, and New York; and her work as a domestic employee, cook, and factory worker. Stackhouse begins by describing her childhood in Rippon, West Virginia, noting that she had a tight-knit, self-sufficient family. She explains that the black community accounted for half of the population in Rippon and notes that race relations were relatively cordial despite segregation in the town. She discusses the history of parts of her family; descriptions of where each of her sisters settled; her family's domestic work for and relationship with the Long family in Rippon; and religious and secular holidays and traditions.
    Stackhouse explains that her desire to leave Rippon came from listening to stories many of her sisters and neighbors related about living in various cities, including New York, New York. She describes moving to Baltimore, Maryland and living with her sisters on Madison Avenue near Druid Hill Park. She recalls different families for whom she worked; her cleaning responsibilities; her ability to create her own schedule; and leaving one employer because of her racist attitude. She discusses working in a department store, a job she found better than domestic work because of its health benefits and worker's compensation. She discusses the stigma associated with domestic work; her and her family's living and working conditions during the Great Depression; dating practices in Baltimore during the 1930s and 40s; the way in which she met and married her husband; and the limited job opportunities available to the black population in the 1940s.
    Stackhouse explains that she moved to New Jersey after her husband was discharged from the Army after World War II and that she acquired domestic work with a family who brought her to New York, New York in 1945. She describes other industries in which she worked, including as a cook at the Rainbow Room at 30 Rockefeller Center in Manhattan; a packer in a garment factory; and as a saleswoman in Macy's. She notes that she enjoyed these jobs more than domestic work because they had less restrictions and allowed her to meet a wide variety of people. She recalls having to adjust her work schedule after her son was born in 1952, giving up her job at Macy's to take care of him when she was unable find a reputable babysitter. Other topics include her husband's employment as a presser in the garment industry and his work for Con Edison; the ways in which women raised families and navigated discriminatory practices at work; a comparison of life in a city and in the country; a comparison of life in the southern and northern United States (US); the typical sequence of a family's migration from the southern to the northern US; and her frequent visits to her remaining family in West Virginia.
  - Stanley, Mary Belle, Undated; 344197 (Box 1, Folder 107)
    Mary Belle Stanley was born Hyde County, North Carolina. Her mother died when she was young, and she was raised by her maternal grandmother. She attended school in North Carolina up to the fourth grade. She migrated to Norfolk, Virginia; Montclair, New Jersey; and later to Brooklyn, New York, where she lived on Gates Avenue for 40 years. She married and had two children. She worked in domestic service, and her husband worked as a longshoreman.
    This interview was conducted by Mary B. Alexander at the Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home in the Bronx, New York. The date is unknown. The audio recording for this interview is missing. Topics of this interview include Mary Belle Stanley's childhood in Hyde County, North Carolina; time spent with her aunt in Norfolk, Virginia; her migration to Montclair, New Jersey and Brooklyn, New York; her work in domestic service; her husband; her leisure and religious activities; and her children.
  - Stein, Yetta, 1972 March 25; 344199 (Box 59, Reel 191a - 191d, Box 1, Folder 80)
    Yetta Stein was born in Nadvirna in the Polish region of Austria-Hungary in the late 19th century. She moved to Vienna during World War I. She married in 1921 and had one daughter. She and her daughter immigrated to the United States in 1938, with her husband following a year later. In 1939, the family moved to St. Louis, Missouri. Stein and her daughter moved to New York, New York in 1945. Stein was a member of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
    This interview was conducted by Karen Kearns on March 25, 1972 at Yetta Stein's apartment in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Yetta Stein's early life in Vienna, Austria-Hungary; her immigration to the United States (US); her marriage; her working life; and her union activity. Stein recounts the rape and pillage by Russian troops in Nadvirna in the Polish region of Austria-Hungary during World War I and the fact that this led her family to flee to Vienna. She describes her life in Vienna as happy but constrained by latent anti-Semitism; the fact that she had many friends who were not Jewish; and her surprise at their overt anti-Semitism once Germany annexed Austria in 1938. She recounts that some of her Jewish friends and family became Austrian citizens, but that she and her husband could not afford to do so, and that this saved their lives as the Nazis had no authority over Polish citizens at that time. She recounts deciding to immigrate to the US in 1938 with her daughter; her husband staying in Vienna as he had no family in the US to sponsor his immigration; and the year her husband spent alone in Vienna destroying his mental health.
    Stein describes a happy life in the US and attributes it to the freedom accorded to all Americans. She explains that she was advised by the National Council of Jewish Women to move to St. Louis, Missouri so that she and her husband could learn trades without having to be members of a union. She describes their apartment in St. Louis and how happy she was there. She recalls that she and her husband both joined the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) in St. Louis. She recalls that the ILGWU helped her find work in a factory in New York City, where she worked for the next 22 years. She describes how much she enjoyed working in the factory; that she liked both the work and her co-workers; and that she made many friends there, both Jewish and West Indian. She describes how important working outside the home was for the women at the factory and the pride they took in their work. She explains the different jobs in the factory; how they were divided between men and women; and the different pay schedules across these jobs. Transcript and index are available for this interview.
  - Sunderman, [Unknown], 1973 April 24; 344200 (Box 60, Reel 192a - 192b, Box 1, Folder 81)
    Mrs. Sunderman was born in Frankfurt, Germany in the late 19th century. Her parents owned a hosiery store. She married and had one daughter. Her husband died in 1938 and she immigrated to the United States (US) two years later. In the US she worked as a housekeeper, companion, and seamstress. She was a member of the Workshop Council of the United Council for Jewish Women.
    This interview was conducted by Karin Young on April 24, 1973. The location is likely the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens in Manhattan, New York. The first name of the narrator is not stated. The interview covers Mrs. Sunderman's life in Germany, her immigration to the United States (US), her family, and her life at the time of the interview. Sunderman recalls her early life in Frankfurt, Germany, including her education. She recounts that both of her parents worked in the family's hosiery store and that their leisure time was spent with other members of the family. She describes her life in Frankfurt before and during World War I. She recounts her decision to send her daughter to the US in 1936 after it became clear there was no future for Jews in Germany. She recalls her immigration to the US in 1940; how free she felt upon her arrival in New York, New York despite how hard she had to work; and that she was glad to have her daughter, other family, and friends nearby. She discusses her life at the time of the interview, including continuing to work as a seamstress at the age of 93.
    See also: Council Workshop for Senior Citizens II; and Life Before Immigration or Migration.
    World War, 1939-1945 |z Germany |v Personal narratives.; World War, 1914-1918 |z Germany |v Personal narratives.
  - Sutton, Kathleen, 1974 April 22 and May 9; 344201 (Box 60, Reel 193a - 193c, Box 61, Reel 193d - 193f, Box 1, Folder 82)
    Kathleen Sutton was born in Limerick, Ireland in 1900. She immigrated to the United States (US) through Ellis Island, New York in 1912. Sutton worked making paper flowers and as a packer for the department stores Macy's and B. Altman and Company. She married in 1925, and was involved in union activity and politics through her husband.
    This interview was conducted on April 22 and May 9, 1974 by Scott Weir at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center in Manhattan, New York. Topics include Kathleen Sutton's childhood in Ireland; her family's immigration to the United States (US); her early life and work experiences in New York, New York; leisure activities and social organizations in which she participated; her marriage and family; her experiences during Prohibition and the Great Depression; and her views on religion and politics. Sutton discusses her childhood in Limerick, Ireland, including the fact that her family was very poor; her father's employment on the docks in Limerick; and her education. She recalls her immigration to the US, including departing from Queenstown, Ireland on the SS Majestic; traveling with her sister and her nephew; and having difficulty obtaining citizenship in the US due to a discrepancy in her name on the ship's manifest. She recalls her early experiences in New York, including feeling lonely and homesick for the first year; being teased due to her accent; being confused about how to use money; interacting with people of different races for the first time; and finding that a majority of the people she met were nice to her because she was from Ireland.
    Sutton discusses her work experience, including her first job making paper flowers; her employment as a packer at both Macy's and B. Altman and Company; her promotion to the mail order department of B. Altman and Company and her dislike of the job due to the lack of socializing; and her limited employment as a telephone operator after her marriage and her dislike of working overnight. She discusses leisure activities in which she participated, including seeing movies and Broadway shows before her marriage; having picnics at Fort George in Manhattan; attending soccer games; and taking walks with her husband every night. She recalls her involvement with the Friends of Irish Freedom, including collecting money to support the 1916 Easter Rising in Ireland; attending dances sponsored by the organization; feeling obligated to join because she was Irish; and continuing to support the movement towards a unified Ireland even though the organization no longer existed at the time of the interview.
    Sutton discusses her husband and his life, including his work as an electrician; his political views; and his involvement in the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers Local 3. She discusses their children and grandchildren, including their two daughters and their personalities and the participation of one of their grandsons in the civil rights movement.
    Sutton discusses her experiences during Prohibition and the Great Depression, including distilling moonshine at a bungalow on Staten Island; obtaining alcohol through a friend who owned a speakeasy; rationing meat and sugar; and learning to use Oleo because of the difficulty obtaining real butter. She discusses religion, including the fact that a majority of her neighbors in the US were Catholic; that priests were seen as infallible; and that she was unlike the rest of her community in that she was not religious. She discusses her dislike of the British because of their treatment of the Irish and the fact that much of her family in Ireland supported the Germans during World War II because they provided weapons to the Irish during the Easter Rising. She recalls her husband's involvement in local politics; her association with many local politicians, including Fiorello La Guardia; and her belief that Irish politicians were trustworthy, while other politicians were only concerned with votes.
    See also: Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York, New York and the United States; Passage; and Politics.
    Depressions |y 1929 |z New York (State) |z New York.; Prohibition |z New York (State) |z New York; Department stores |x Employees |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Tamovitz, Israel, 1975 March 24; 344202 (Box 61, Reel 194a - 194b)
    Israel Tamovitz was born Vilna, Russia. He was one of six children and had two brothers and three sisters. His father worked for a freight station in Vilna while his mother stayed home and cared for the children. Tamowitz immigrated to the United States (US) in 1910 in order to avoid being drafted into the Russian Army. He paid an agent to smuggle him out of Russia and traveled to the US, arriving at Ellis Island, New York. He settled in Pennsylvania with his brother. He worked as a salesman both in Russia and in the US. While in Russia, he was an active member of the General Jewish Labour Bund of Lithuania, Poland, and Russia.
    This interview was conducted by Francis Facciolo on March 24, 1975 at an unknown location. This interview covers Israel Tamovitz's life in Vilna, Russia; his involvement in the General Jewish Labour Bund of Lithuania, Poland, and Russia; his immigration to the United States (US) in 1910; and some of his life in Pennsylvania. Tamovitz begins by explaining his involvement in the Bund, noting that he learned about the organization through word of mouth; began attending meetings held in the woods; and keeping his coworkers informed about demonstrations and proclamations against the czar. He discusses the relationships among factions within and outside of the organization; the relationship between the people and the police; Tamovitz's arrest; and his brother's involvement in the Bund.
    Tamovitz recalls that his initial impression of the US was that of a beautiful, free country in which every person could go where he wanted and stay informed of government policies. He describes the development of an unspecified miners' union in the Pennsylvania town where he settled; the impact John Mitchell and the miners' unions had on working conditions; and the decline of mining, which forced workers into other industrial occupations and trades. Other topics include his brother's immigration to the US and the fate of members of his family that remained in Vilna during World War I and World War II.
    Coal miners |x Labor unions |z United States.
  - Tannenbaum, Rose, 1973 April 30; 344203 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    Rose Tannenbaum was born in 1896 in the Lithuanian region of the Russian Empire. Her grandfather was a lumber merchant. She immigrated to the United States when she was 16 years old. She lived in Lancaster, Pennsylvania; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; and New York, New York. She married and had one son. She worked in a wholesale sweater business and belonged to B'nai B'rith International.
    This interview was conducted by Victor Scheluchin on April 30, 1973 at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Rose Tannenbaum's family and her working life in the United States (US).
    Tannenbaum recounts her reasons for immigrating to the US, including an impending pogrom in her town and general anti-Semitism in the Russian Empire. She recounts immigrating to the US with two of her brothers; her mother and her remaining siblings immigrating to Austria; and her father and grandfather remaining in Lithuania. She recounts settling in Lancaster, Pennsylvania upon her arrival in the US; moving to Philadelphia; working in a five-and-ten; and meeting and marrying her husband. She discusses moving to New York, New York with her husband; his work as a music salesman; and her enjoyment of her work in a wholesale sweater business. Other topics include the deaths of her family in Austria and Israel during World War II (WWII); her travels to Europe before WWII to visit her family; and her attendance at Brooklyn College to study Hebrew and an unidentified school on 14th Street in Manhattan to study Russian.
  - Taranto, Raphael, 1975 March 24; 344204 (Box 62, Reel 196a)
    Raphael Taranto was born near Sicily, Italy in 1890. He had six sisters and four brothers. He first immigrated to the United States (US) in 1908 and stayed with his brother and uncle but returned to Italy in 1911 to serve in the Italian Army. He married his wife while in Italy and returned to the US in 1918. He worked as a longshoreman and was a member of the International Longshoremen's Association Local 1814. His wife worked in the garment industry and was a member of an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union).
    This interview was conducted by John Jentz on March 24, 1975 at the Carroll Gardens Senior Center at 380 Court Street in Brooklyn, New York. A second interviewer, identified as Frank, joins the interview after 20 minutes. Raphael Taranto speaks predominantly in Italian and is assisted by a translator, John Laccari. The volume of this recording fluctuates.
    This interview covers Raphael Taranto's immigration to the United States (US) in 1908; his return to Italy to serve in the Italian Army between 1911 and 1918; and his work as a longshoreman in the US. Taranto begins by describing the reasons he immigrated to the US, explaining that he believed that he could have a better life there. He discusses working as a longshoreman in Brooklyn, New York until 1955 and joining Local 1814 of the International Longshoremen's Association (ILA). Other topics include the development of Local 1814 and the ILA; segregation and discrimination among different immigrant groups; and a comparison of living conditions in New York City in the past and at the time of the interview.
  - Terranova, Benny, 1973 April 12; 344206 (Box 62, Reel 198a - 198b, Box 1, Folder 84)
    Benny Terranova was born in 1912 in Brooklyn, New York and was one of eleven children. His parents were born in Sicily, Italy. His father owned a bakery in Brooklyn. Terranova graduated from Public School 103 and attended Stuyvesant High School in Manhattan for a year and a half before leaving school to work with his father. He worked as a baker and as a longshoreman. He was a member of an unspecified Italian bakers' union and the International Longshoremen's Association (ILA). He was an official and president of an unspecified local (likely Local 1814) of the ILA. He married in 1940.